The first ever reality-based movie ... everything begins and ends in 30 days!
Super Size Me is a documentary film directed by Morgan Spurlock.
Morgan Spurlock subjects himself to a diet based only on McDonald's fast food three times a day for
thirty days without exercising to try to prove why so many Americans are fat or obese.
He submits himself to a complete check-up by three doctors, comparing his
weight along the way, resulting in a scary conclusion.
Self, played by Morgan Spurlock.
Self - Internal Medicine, played by Daryl Isaacs.
Self - Gastroenterologist & Hepatologist, played by Lisa Ganjhu.
Self - Cardiologist, played by Stephen Siegel.
Self - Nutritionist & Dietician, played by Bridget Bennett.
Self - Exercise Physiologist, played by Eric Rowley.
Super Size Me is a 2004 American documentary film directed by and
starring Morgan Spurlock, an American independent filmmaker.
Spurlock's film follows a 30-day period from February 1 to March 2, 2003, during which he claimed to
consume only McDonald's food, although he later disclosed he was also abusing alcohol.
The film documents the drastic change on Spurlock's
physical and psychological health and well-being.
It also explores the fast food industry's corporate influence, including how
it encourages poor nutrition for its own profit and gain.
The film prompted widespread debate about American eating habits and has since come under scrutiny
for the accuracy of its science and the truthfulness of Spurlock's on-camera claims.
Spurlock ate at McDonald's restaurants three times a day,
consuming every item on the chain's menu at least once.
Spurlock claimed to have consumed an average of 20.9 megajoules or 5,000 kcal
(the equivalent of 9.26 Big Macs) per day during the experiment.
He also walked about 2 kilometers (1.5 miles) a day.
An intake of around 2,500 kcal within a healthy balanced diet is more
generally recommended for a man to maintain his weight.
At the end of the experiment the then-32-year-old Spurlock had gained 24.5 pounds (11.1 kg), a 13% body mass increase, increased his
cholesterol to 230 mg/dL (6.0 mmol/L), and experienced mood swings, sexual dysfunction, and fat accumulation in his liver.
The reason for Spurlock's investigation was the increasing spread of obesity throughout US society, which the surgeon general has declared an "epidemic", and the
corresponding lawsuit brought against McDonald's on behalf of two overweight girls, who, it was alleged, became obese as a result of eating McDonald's food (Pelman v.
McDonald's Corporation, 237 F.
Spurlock argued that, although the lawsuit against McDonald's failed (and subsequently many state legislatures have legislated against product liability actions against producers and distributors of "fast food"),
as well as the McLibel case, much of the same criticism leveled against the tobacco companies applies to fast food franchises whose product is both physiologically addictive and physically harmful.
The documentary was nominated for an Academy Award for Best Documentary Feature, and
won Best Documentary Screenplay from the Writers Guild of America.
Dark Horse Comics subsequently published a comic book related to the movie,
containing stories based on numerous cases of fast food health scares.
Spurlock released a sequel, Super Size Me 2: Holy Chicken!, in 2017.
The film explores themes of experiment, diet, junk food, health, food.